linkedin.com/in/jpcercal github.com/jpcercal

About me

I've been working with PHP since 2009, I'm a Zend Certified PHP Engineer working with Agile, always looking for best practices and methodologies to improve my workflow and so bring great results to the project and all stakeholders. A developer that likes writing tests, enjoys learning new design-patterns, loves code "well written" (a balance is always essential), and reads about 20 books per year.

Experience

Turbine Kreuzberg

Senior Software Engineer

Currently

- Making the most of PHP and the Spryker framework/ecosystem expertise to design, develop, and maintain robust e-commerce solutions, ensuring the efficient functioning of digital platforms;
- Optimizing e-commerce performance through meticulous code craftsmanship and a comprehensive understanding of the Spryker framework, directly leading to enhanced user experiences, faster page loading times, and increased conversion rates for our clients;
- Collaboratively solving complex challenges within our agile development environment, actively collaborating with cross-functional teams to address complex challenges, utilizing problem-solving skills and technical expertise to devise innovative solutions that drive the success of our large-scale e-commerce projects.

Spectrm

Senior Software Engineer

2020 - 2022

- Making a significant impact on the market by helping top-tier companies engage consumers effectively through innovative marketing chatbots on major messaging platforms. This led to substantial sales growth and boosted brand loyalty;
- By designing, developing, and launching scalable solutions to tackle intricate business challenges with an enduring focus on scalability, I significantly enhanced operational efficiency, expanded the company's market presence, and secured long-term adaptability, propelling the business to new heights;
- Led backend chapter meetings, mentored junior developers, and played a crucial role in defining migration strategies for vital platform changes;
- Championed architectural decision records (ADRs), conducted post-mortems, and facilitated lightning talks to foster a culture of continuous improvement within the engineering team.

GetYourGuide

Senior Software Engineer

2018 - 2020

■ Impacting and changing the way how millions of travelers connect to the places they visit, in combination with rigorous A/B testing to craft an unbeatable e-commerce. In numbers, during the last semester, my team created about 20 experiments and I worked with 4 of them, in which the last one that I've worked on increased the conversion rate in almost 2%;

- Aligning the product with technical decisions while having the customer at first, but also considering data over guessing have guided me to influence in a killer feature to contact us through WhatsApp in which our travelers can get support from their smartphones. It increased the second customer purchase metric considerably and helped us to retain customers;
- Doing interviews, providing long detailed feedback right after it to the talents while suggesting improvements to the overall process to hire the best people as a consequence developing a really good product;
- Test-driven oriented, impacting the way that engineers see unit test bringing then, the quality of the product to the next level.

FlixBus

Senior PHP Developer

2017 - 2018

- Changing the life of approximately one billion of people commuting, spending their weekends, building remote relationships, visiting relatives, and discovering the world;
- We improved the response time for retrieving a cart in almost 70% by extracting the code from the monolith to a new micro-service-oriented architecture;
- Volunteer to be a facilitator in agile ceremonies such as retrospective and sprint review;
- Responsible for taking decisions from a technical perspective regarding our domain.

NeoGrid

Senior PHP Developer

2015 - 2017

- Created a web application using Material Design and AngularJS to the front-end and Silex to the backend, which automated the sales of the WebEDI solution scaling the business and reducing in about 40% the costs for selling the product;
- Implemented improvements, bug fixes and integrations with NeoGrid solutions by delivering REST APIs;
- Added the Vagrant tool in order to have the development environment as close as possible to our production server;
- Evangelist of best practices of programming following the existent PSRs and implementing unit test in the projects;
- Reference in my team to projects that were written in either PHP or JS.

Education

UNISOCIESC

BSc Information Systems

2011 - 2014

- I was presented as the best graduating student;
- The final paper was based on a tool created to be used by professionals that are studying to achieve the ZCPE certification, the project is open-source and it's available on GitHub, the web app has been hosted by "DigitalOcean" as a sponsor.